Exactly.
בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today is דף ע"א, Daf Ayin Aleph, 71,
we pick up a few lines in. And I will remind you
about the case. The case here is that a person first forgot
it was שבת Shabbat and did two מלאכות, melachot, cutting and grinding.
And then they somehow remembered it was שבת Shabbat and forgot you
can't do these מלאכות, melachot, without having realized that they had just
sinned. And then did the same two things again, but now forgetting
that grinding and cutting are prohibited. So that means that if you
were to look at that in isolation, that would be two sin
offerings. And now they went ahead and then they remembered their sins,
but also sequentially. So I'm just going to draw that again, right?
In the first space, basically one, the first sin is one because
also it's one forgetting of שבת Shabbat which would lead to two
sin offerings. And then they did the forgetting of the two acts,
but they remembered that it was
שבת. Shabbat. And then they remembered, and they remembered in the same
order. Okay? First they remember their first sin, which was the forgetting
of שבת, Shabbat, and then their second sin. And once they remembered
their first sin, their act of remembering creates the obligation of the
קרבן. korban. So then that leads to here, they have to bring
this קרבן, korban, and this קרבן korban is for two things, קצירה
ktzira and טחינה. tchina. Okay?
And then they remembered this, so everything that they remembered should lead
to a separate קרבן. korban. Okay? But קצירה ktzira and טחינה. tchina.
But because they had already obligated themselves in one קרבן, korban, they
do not obligate themselves in this second קרבן korban because this קצירה
ktzira is already included in an obligation of קצירה ktzira and this
טחינה tchina sin is already for that. Now, Michael asked me at
the end of day yesterday after the שיעור, shiur, that normally we
say that when things are done in two acts of forgetting, they
are two separate קרבנות. korbanot. So if I, for example, forget that
you're not allowed to eat חמץ chametz on פסח, Pesach, and I
eat חמץ, chametz, and then I remember in the middle of the
day, and then I forget again and I eat חמץ chametz again,
that's two קרבנות. korbanot. Although it's the exact same sin, it's two
קרבנות korbanot because I forgot in the middle.
Even though, and not only that, even though the remembering in the
middle obligated me in the first one, you know, but it doesn't
matter, separate things,
and therefore it's separate. If I have a straight state of forgetting
and I do multiple sins, that's one קרבן. korban. So רש"י Rashi
actually addresses that, and רש"י Rashi says this is a little different,
because this is, it's not really a different forgetting. This is a
forgetting of שבת Shabbat and this is a forgetting of the מלאכות.
melachot. So on the other hand, it is in one basically continuous
ignorance, but ignorance at different stages about different things. It's not like
in the middle you became aware of your mistake. Okay? So because
of that ambiguity, that on the one hand it's not two completely
separate acts of forgetting, there's not a remembering in between, on the
other hand it's not completely the same because you're forgetting different things
at different times, that allows for this discussion. That's basically what רש"י
Rashi says. So I just wanted to acknowledge that that's an excellent
point, that, you know, why do we have two קרבנות korbanot here,
and that's because this is very ambivalent right here. On the one
hand there's not a remembering in between, so it's not absolutely two
קרבנות, korbanot, and on the other hand it's not exactly the same
state of forgetting, it's different things you're forgetting, so it has the
possibility of conflating into one קרבן. korban. And the way the גמרא
Gemara says to resolve it, at least in this stage, is if
this first became obligated, then that's, this is already included in that.
That's the easy case. The more complicated case is that you remembered
in the reverse order. First you remembered from your two thing, but
you only remembered one of them, the קצירה. ktzira. Then you remembered
one, then you remembered two, the טחינה. tchina. Okay, so you remembered
this act, but only part of it, and then that act and
only part of it. Okay, so here you're obligated in this one
קרבן, korban, your קצירה ktzira קרבן. korban. Then here, do you become
obligated in this? Well, because this is קצירה גוררת קצירה, ktzira goreret
ktzira, part of this קרבן korban is already being brought for this,
part of what this is for is already being brought for this,
you don't have to bring that קרבן. korban. It's already somehow, you
know, included in that. Although interestingly, you won't get the atonement for
the טחינה, tchina, but anyway, part of it is already
included in that. That's what רבא Rava says. Okay, fine, that's what
רבא Rava says. אביי Abaye says, once you don't have to bring
for this, then even when you remember this, you don't have to
because this is included in this. So the טחינה tchina is included
in this, and this is included in this, so this becomes the
sufficient one to bring, which doesn't make so much sense because this
has no representation in that one, but nevertheless, that's what אביי Abaye
says. Okay, so that's where we have left off. You know what,
I'll read it again just from the top, just to, but then
we will. Let's read it. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
starting from the top of ע"א עמוד א': ayin-aleph amud-aleph: קצירה גוררת
קצירה וטחינה גוררת טחינה. ktzirah goreret ktzirah vetachina goreret tachina. That's in
the first case where you remembered in the same order 1, 2,
1, 2. So the first obligation, which was the קרבן korban for
both, drags along the second obligations, the second קרבנות, korbanot, which are
included in the first one. אבל נודע לו אקצירה של זדון שבת
ושגגת מלאכות. aval nodah lo aktzirah shel zadon shabbat veshiggat melachot. Let's
say you remembered 2, 1, 2, and the first one you remembered
was קצירה, ktzirah, then you remembered the one thing that had both,
and then the final טחינה. tachina. In that case, קצירה גוררת קצירה
וטחינה שעמה. ktzirah goreret ktzirah vetachina she'imah. The קצירה, ktzirah, the first
קרבן, korban, drags with it—drags, like, includes in itself—the second קרבן korban
that has קצירה ktzirah plus the טחינה tachina part of it, even
though that wasn't represented in the first קרבן. korban. But since there's
somewhat overlap, bringing that קצירה ktzirah obligation enough includes the second one.
וטחינה שכנגדה, vetachina shekenegdah, when you remembered the second טחינה, tachina, number
two, במקומו עומדת, bimkomo omedet, then you'll have to bring a separate
קרבן korban for that. Alright, that's pretty reasonable according to רבא, Rava,
and at least according to that, you're bringing once an offering for
קצירה, ktzirah, once for טחינה tachina at the end of the day.
Okay,
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אביי Abaye says:
טחינה נמי גוררת טחינה. tachina nami goreret tachina. The
טחינה tachina of number one here drags along the טחינה tachina of
number two, even though you're not bringing this, even though you're only
bringing this one. Okay, שום טחינה אחת היא, shum tachina achat hi,
it's all considered one category of טחינה. tachina. So according to אביי,
Abaye, you're only bringing one קרבן korban for קצירה, ktzirah, and somehow
that covers all of the various sins you did, even though no
קרבן korban is specifically for the act of טחינה. tachina. That is
what אביי Abaye says. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara focuses first
on רבא. Rava. ומי אית ליה לרבא גררה? Umi is lei lerava
grera? Does רבא Rava really hold of this idea of dragging? Meaning
that in this case, this קרבן, korban, which is only for the
קצירה, ktzirah, can include, drag along, this one, which is supposed to
be for two things, קצירה ktzirah and
טחינה. tachina. So the גמרא Gemara questioning whether רבא Rava really says
that, because there's another statement of רבא Rava that would seem to
to not be saying this. Let's take a look. Yes,
קצירה ktzirah is cutting and טחינה tachina is grinding. So they're just
two separate acts that you've done, right? We could have said watering
your plants and cooking food. Okay. So, but just sort of speak
about like A and B is really the point. Okay. So והאיתמר,
vehaitmar, but didn't we say:
אכל שני זיתי חלב? achal shene zayte chelev? You ate
two—זיתי—חלב, excuse me, thank you. You ate two olives' worth of forbidden
fat, which is punishable by כרת, karet, which means that if you
did it without awareness, you'd bring a קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. Now,
as Michael has told us, or as I mentioned, בהעלם אחד, behelem
echad, that is in one state of forgetfulness. So even if you
ate them at different times of the day, or even, you know,
different times in the week, if you're in one state of having
forgotten that this piece of meat is חלב, chelev, or that חלב
chelev, was forbidden, and you didn't wake up and realize in between,
then it all is one קרבן. korban. Although they're separate acts—right, it's
not תוך כדי אכילת פרס—right, toch kede achilat pras it could be
on a different day of the week, but because it's one state
of forgetfulness, even for those different acts, one קרבן korban suffices. בהעלם
אחד. behelem echad. Now, what happened? ונודע לו
על אחת מהן. venodah lo al achat mehen. Then you became aware
of your first act or one of them. וחזר ואכל כזית בהעלמו
של שני, vechazar ve'achal kizayit behelemos shel sheni, and then you ate
a third כזית. kizayit. Having fun yet?
Here is the case. The case is you had three כזיתי חלב.
kezayte chelev. I keep—I don't know why I do
that, okay, thinking Hanukkah, I guess, or maybe. Okay, חלב. chelev Okay,
you have three כזיתים kezaytes of חלב. chelev. One, you have two,
you have three. You have these three כזיתים. kezaytes. Okay. So you
ate these two in one state of forgetting. Okay. Forgetting,
this is your forgetting—your state of forgetting A. Okay. Then you
realized—you know, what should we do here, a little light bulb?
Oh, look at that! Anyway, anyway, whatever. You realized that you had
eaten the first one. Okay. You still didn't realize you ate the
second one. You forgot about what you had done. You still weren't
aware of your sin, but you were aware of your first sin,
and then you went ahead and you ate the third one. So
when you ate the third one, it was in the same state
of unawareness of number two, right? You get that? Because you had—these
were done without being aware that you had sinned with either of
those. They were done in the same state of unawareness. So that's
your forgetting B. Okay, that's what you have done now. Okay. So
how many קרבנות korbanot do you bring? Right? And then you become
aware—here, here you get your—your lightbulb again, whatever—you become aware of two
and three. Okay, now you become aware. So how many קרבנות korbanot
do you bring? That is the question. Let's take a look. Okay,
but it's obvious that it's two. Okay, is there
any. Is there any scenario you would only bring one קרבן? korban?
If it
was all
one, if you remember at the very end,
let's take a look what it says, okay?
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says
רבא, Rava, הבי קרבן על ראשון ראשון ושני מתכפרין שלישי אינו מתכפר.
Hevi korban al rishon rishon u'sheni mitkaprim shelishi eino mitkaper. If you
bring for the first one, then that includes, that atones for sins
one and two, but not in sin number three.
הבי קרבן על שלישי, Hevi korban al shelishi, if you bring the
קרבן korban for the third
כזית, kezayit, שלישי ושני מתכפרין, shelishi u'sheni mitkaprim, that atones for sins
three and two, ראשון אינו מתכפר, rishon eino mitkaper, not for sin
one. But if you're really smart, הבי קרבן על אמצעי, Hevi korban
al emtzai, say this קרבן korban is for the middle, is for
sin number two, and in that case נתכפרו כולם, niskapru kulam, they
all get atoned for, okay? If you are bringing for this sin,
well this sin is the same category, it's for the same state
of forgetfulness, so the קרבן korban here for number one includes act
number two. The קרבן korban for number three is in this state
of forgetfulness, so that includes act, so three includes two. But if
you're really smart, you'll bring the קרבן korban for having eaten number
two, and then that is both the same state of forgetfulness of
one and from another side, on its father's side it's one, on
its mother's side it's three, and therefore the קרבן korban for two
represents both of those two, to, both of those sins and you
only have to bring one קרבן. korban. Okay, so questions? Yes.
First of all, let's say I want to bring a קרבן korban
on all, would that work?
No,
I don't think you have that option. It is funny because that's
then just a חולין לעזרה. chullin la-azarah. The reality is that they
are objectively defined. The point still funny is that you're bringing one
קרבן korban and you get to designate which is the primary sin
that this is being brought for and which are the other ones
that are being schlepped along. So that's a little funny that there
isn't an objective way of defining that. Yes.
One further thing, just like usually we say that things have to
separate the forgetfulness in the bottom case, you know, bottom case you
remember two and one or two and whatever, you know. Right. Is
something separating the remembrances? In other words, let's say I'm all processing
it right away. Yeah. So then. Even if I process like instantaneously
in my mind two, which, does that still count? Or do I
wait an hour?
No, no, no, no, no, if you remember it at all, then
all your חיובים chiyuvim come at the same time.
So I'm like waiting an hour or remembering as I go along.
Yeah. But that doesn't have to be that way, yeah.
But I thought that you only remembered on the first one.
No, and then you remembered on two and three. That's not being
said, but that's implicit.
Because then what do you show for?
That's my lightbulb,
I had the two קרבנות. korbanot. What?
No, because if you bring your קרבן korban for number two.
I didn't know about number two.
What? You become aware over here.
I'll bring the קרבן korban then.
You don't bring the קרבן korban now, you just become aware now,
you become obligated now. Okay.
So maybe I should, I should not bring the קרבן korban on
first one in case I didn't realize I was doing a mistake?
I'm not going to tell you what you should do. You, you
didn't get around to it and then you realized. No, of course
not. Over here, when you remembered over here, you're not aware you've
done anything else wrong. We can't advise you, don't bring it yet,
maybe you did something wrong and you're not aware. Okay, but we're
not talking to you here. You're coming to the בית דין beit
din over here, you're coming to the רב rabbi over here and
asking your שאלה. shaila. You're not asking your שאלה shaila over there.
And he can
tell you go
bring it for the second one?
Yeah. Okay, so that's רבא. Rava. Now.
Okay, so now is רבא. Rava. Okay, so now אביי אומר, Abaye
omer, now wait, אביי Abaye says, if you thought רבא Rava was
interesting, אביי Abaye says, אפילו הביא קרבן על אחד מהן, afilu hevi
korban al echad mehen, you can bring on any one, bring on
one, bring on three, I don't care. נתכפרו כולם. niskapru kulam. They
all get, they all get atoned for. Why? Because of this idea
of גררה. gera. Let's say you bring on three, if I'm bringing
on three, it also includes two. But if two is being included
in my קרבן, korban, well one is included in the קרבן korban
of two, right? So since, or the same in the reverse, I
bring on one, the קרבן korban for number one includes the sin
number two, but sin number two, the, you know, a קרבן korban
for number two would include sin number three. So therefore on any
one, it drags the other one with it.
And that's consistent with what he said about the שבת. Shabbat.
Right. Although here, he said it even more extreme. The reason this
is more extreme is because in this scenario, nothing represents the sin
of תחינה. tchinah. At least in this case, everything's for the sin
of חלב. chelev. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara actually thinks that this
is a lighter type of a גררה, gera, it's not as big
of a גררה gera as dragging something that isn't even represented, it's
a lighter type of a גררה gera and still רבא Rava disagrees.
So if רבא Rava doesn't allow the one, two, three, says the
גמרא, Gemara, how does he allow, you know, this to be dragged
along with that if this isn't completely identical? This has a part
that is not included in number one, this has the תחינה tchinah
part. So that's the גמרא Gemara sees those as roughly analogous, a
little discussion of רש״י Rashi תוספות Tosafot exactly how to draw that,
but the basic point is since this in one hand is pretty
similar to על חלב al chelev and on the other hand it's
a lit, it's like not exactly included in this one because this
is, you know, two degrees removed. So here too, it's there's some
similarity but there's a part of it which is not included and
therefore how does רבא... Rava... allow for this case if he doesn't
allow that case? Let's let's see—I thank you—let's see the answer. So
the גמרא Gemara says, בתר דשמעיה מאביי סברה. batar deshameih me'Abaye savrah.
Okay, after he had the first debate with אביי, Abaye, he was
persuaded by אביי's Abaye logic, so he therefore actually reversed himself, and
therefore, you know what, if he went back to that case, he
would say bring it for one or three, that would be fine.
Wait, even the bottom case, the שבת Shabbat case?
No, and therefore, no, the שבת Shabbat he still doesn't argue to
that extent when it's not included, when it's, you know, when there's
nothing that overlaps with the first, with the one you're bringing forward.
But the basic idea that there could be some way that the
one drags the other, that he's willing to concede. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, אי הכי i hachi basically asks Michael's question,
אי הכי תחנה נמי תגרר. i hachi techina nami tigarrer. Once you're
buying into this idea of גררה, grera, why do you say that
number two gets dragged along, I mean that the number one gets
dragged along in this case, the combined קרבן, korban, why doesn't it
then also drag the other one? So the גמרא Gemara says,
תחנה נמי תגרר לתחנה, techina nami tigarrer le'techina, let the תחנה techina
in the grinding in number one drag the grinding sin of number
two. So the גמרא Gemara says, גררה אית ליה גררה דגררה לית
ליה. grera it lei grera de'grera leit lei. Okay, he has one
dragging, not two draggings. Okay, now of course, so therefore this can
drag this, but it can't drag this. But it's not only that
it's like two degrees removed, I mean again רש"י Rashi helps us
try to figure out the exact parameters, but the basic point is
is that this is not even included really in this first one,
and that sort of makes this, you know, this is too far
removed. So this type of a thing he can, right, because this
does drag in a way, you know, this includes this, that includes
that, it's not just a question of are there two or are
there three, it's that in this case it's a dragging of a
dragging so that the last one isn't at all represented in the
first one, and that's already too far for him. Yes, Michael. The
question is though, I
mean, what I was trying to say is that they're fundamentally different
because in the שבת Shabbat case you have X and then X
are followed by subsequent remembrances, all the Xs are completed and the
remembrances are done, you know, in a separate sphere. Right. But in
the other case it's X and remembrances and then X. So you
know, you could say, I mean, that they're just different, just the
way these things are structured. You know, and therefore since Xs are
dividing—since remembrances—yeah,
I mean there are all those differences. You know, again, there's always
a question when there's differences between the cases, are they substantive or
not? Are they enough to categorize them differently? The גמרא Gemara assumes
here that there's enough similarity, it could have I guess, it could
have found a way to distinguish it. Then we would have been
breaking our heads why those, you know, why those differences should really
make a difference, you know, why are they substantive enough? So anyway,
let's, but yeah, of course, there are those differences in the case.
All right, so that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. So let's continue. The
גמרא Gemara says like
this, one
minute,
right, one minute, I'm just double checking רש"י Rashi one minute.
Does anyone want to address what I asked?
No.
Okay, fine.
Right. רש"י Rashi says it just a little slightly differently which is,
I mean, that not just that this תחנה techina isn't represented in
the first קרבן korban but that this thing is being dragged because
of its קצירה. ketzira. So therefore it doesn't have the power to
drag something else based on a different aspect of it, of the
תחנה techina aspect. Same type of idea though, that this תחנה techina
is totally foreign to this original first one, and therefore that's something
that אביי—that Abaye רבא Rava is not willing to concede. So now
the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so מילתא
דפשיטא ליה לאביי ורבא, milta de'pshita lei le'Abaye ve'Rava, the thing that
was obvious to אביי Abaye and רבא Rava that at least there's
some degree of גררה grera or some degree in which one קרבן
korban can be included in the other, at least the first case
they all agree that if first you remember number one and then
number two that you didn't bring number two at all, that thing
that was obvious to אביי Abaye and
רבא, Rava, איבעיא ליה לרבי זירא, ibaia lei le'Rabbi Zeira, was actually
something that רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira himself wasn't certain of, the thing
they took for granted. דבעי רבי זירא, de'ba'ei Rabbi Zeira, because
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira asked מרבי אסי, mi'Rabbi Assi, ואמרי לה בעי
מיניה רבי ירמיה מרבי זירא, ve'amri lah ba'ei mineih Rabbi Yirmiyah mi'Rabbi
Zeira, some say it was רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah who asked רבי
זירא. Rabbi Zeira. קצר וטחן חצי גרוגרת בשגגת שבת וזדון
מלאכות וחזר וקצר וטחן חצי גרוגרת בזדון שבת ושגגת מלאכות.
katzar ve'tachan chatzi grogeret be'shigagat Shabbat
ve'zadon melachot ve'chazar ve'katzar ve'tachan chatzi grogeret be'zadon Shabbat ve'shigagat melachot. So
this idea of two different ways of forgetting, okay,
but rather than speaking about two קרבנות korbanot we're going to speak
about is it considered one consistent state to combine two acts to
one? What do we mean?
First, I forgot לשבת le'Shabbat and I, you know,
let's make an easier example. I forgot it was שבת Shabbat and
I wrote one letter. Here they're saying I cut something that was
half the size of, you know, of a fig, so it was
half the prohibited size. But I'll give you an easier example. So
I wrote one letter on a piece of paper, I wrote the
שין shin from שם sheim or whatever. I’m thinking that it was
Wednesday. Okay, then I remembered, oh my gosh, it’s שבת, Shabbos, but
somehow I totally forgot you’re not allowed to write on שבת, Shabbos,
and I wrote the מם. Mem. Okay, so now I’ve done a
whole מלאכה melacha with half of it, half of it
with forget, one type of forgetting, forgetting that was שבת, Shabbos, the
other with the other type of forgetting, forgetting that you’re not allowed
to write on שבת. Shabbos. I didn’t remember in the middle, I
didn’t put two and two together and realize that I had sinned.
There was no realization. There was just two separate ways of forgetting,
okay, and each one was half of a מלאכה. melacha. Is it
considered one state of forgetfulness because I didn’t remember? But there were
two different ways of forgetting in order to say that I’ve done
a מלאכה. melacha. Or are they two separate things, and they don’t
combine to say I’ve done a מלאכה? melacha? That, and then yeah,
then I’ll get off the hook. So that’s the question.
מהו? Mahu? מהו שיצטרפו? Mahu sheyitztarfu? Do they combine? אמר ליה, Amar
lei, חלוקין לחטאות ולא מצטרפין. Chalukin l'chatos v'lo mitztarfin. Since, if you
had done two full acts in those different states of forgetfulness, you
would have to bring two separate sin offerings, therefore those are complete,
they are considered completely separate states, and they do not combine. Okay,
so his basic answer was they don’t combine, but how do I
know they don’t combine? Because if you did two full acts, you
would next, you would have to bring two separate קרבנות. korbanos. Well,
that’s our basic case. Two full acts, no remembering, different states of
forgetting, and in all the scenarios we gave, especially the simple scenario,
right, of the one and the two, what do we say? We
say you bring קרבן korban once since this has both and you
don’t have to bring קרבן korban two. But he said look, since
these ideas of different states of forgetfulness, even without a remembering in
the middle, is enough to say when you do remember, you will
always bring two קרבנות, korbanos, so therefore I don’t care what is
not going to be included, you’ll always bring two, then this is
considered totally separate states, totally separate acts, and therefore a half and
a half also won’t combine. So what we see is, is that
he actually assumes the opposite of אביי Abaye and רבא, Rava, that
when you, that because these are different states of forgetfulness, even though
there’s no remembering, they can be no combining for קרבנות. korbanos. The
קרבנות korbanos will separate, totally separate, and therefore the two halves will
also remain separate. Does that make sense? No, the question was, then
that was the answer. The question was do these two combine? And
the answer was no, they don’t. They’re fully separate. They’re separate for
different קרבנות korbanos and they’re separate to divide the two halves of
the act. Okay, so different states of forgetfulness are completely not, do
not combine. Yes.
I was just wondering, is this
really serious discussion because... Right.
No. No, if I could
analyze
why I forgot...
look, this is one of those גמרות Gemaros where, you know, they’re
just, it’s a, it is, I think, a very interesting, you know,
contrast to the first six פרקים. perakim. The first six פרקים perakim
not only were like practical cases—can I do this, can I do
that, when do I light my candles, how do I put the
stuff—but it also like really embedded us in the material world of
the time of, you know, that this was being written, like what
all the clothes looked like and, you know, really got, you know,
was really deeply embedded in reality. This is a stark contrast. A,
it’s like not really, nobody’s asking these practical questions. It’s completely abstract.
There’s nothing about the real lived world. This is a part of
the גמרא Gemara where they are playing with these halakhic concepts and
trying to determine like the exact parameters, but not in the context
of something that’s like a real case. It’s not in the real,
it’s not, yeah, there’s no... right, right, it’s one of these... correct,
it’s one of these, it’s one of these academic abstract questions and
it really is very starkly contrasting to the earlier פרקים. perakim. Most
cases in the גמרא Gemara fall somewhere between the first פרקים perakim
and this. Meaning there’s a certain abstract intellectual element, but there’s a
practical as well, but it’s not so much deeply embedded in the
material world, you know. Here there’s a real stark contrast between the
two types of issues that we’ve been discussing. Yes.
And no one had brought a קרבן korban at that point for
over 200 years...
Right. These are just, this is just an intellectual question, an academic
question. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So that,
so anyway, that the answer was the question was do they combine
or not and the answer was no, they absolutely do not combine,
totally separate. So that’s against the assumption of אביי Abaye and רבא.
Rava. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to now ask that
question. Do we say if things are separate to bring separate קרבן,
korban, they’re also separate to get you off the hook and to
say that two halves don’t make a whole? So let’s take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכל היכא דחלוקין לחטאות לא מצטרפי?
v'chol heicha d'chalukin l'chatos lo mitztarfi? Is it really true that if
things are divided acts and it brings separate sin offerings, then they’re
completely considered divided and it wouldn’t... combine two halves? והתנן, vehitnan, let's
look at a משנה Mishnah in כריתות, Kerisos, אכל חלב וחלב בהעלם
אחד אינו חייב אלא אחת. achal chelev vechelev behe'elam echad eino chayav
ela achas. There you go what we've been assuming before, you ate
a כזית kezayis of fat and a כזית kezayis of fat in
one state of forgetfulness, one sin offering.
אכל חלב ודם ונותר ופיגול בהעלם אחד. achal chelev vedam venotar ufigul
behe'elam echad. You did five separate things... did I say five?
No, I said a busy day.
Okay, right, busy day. So you did four separate things which all
of them are חייב כרת, chayav kares, so all of them if
you did it בשוגג beshogeg you'd bring a חטאת. chatas. So fat
and blood and נותר notar and פיגול pigul which are four separate
things which are different sort of קרבנות, korbanot, you know, that you
intended to eat at the wrong time or you left over at
the wrong time, all things חייב כרת. chayav kares. Okay, בהעלם אחד,
behe'elam echad, one state of forgetfulness. Now in that case, חייב על
כל אחת ואחת. chayav al kol achas ve'achas. It doesn't matter, they
were four separate categories of things, four separate sins. So therefore you
bring four separate sin offerings. זו חומר במינין הרבה ממין אחד. zu
chomer beminin harbe mimi echad. In that way if you have multiple
categories like multiple different sins, it leads to a stringency because you'll
bring four קרבנות korbanot as opposed to one קרבן. korban. But let's
give you a reverse case. וזו חומר, vezu chomer, the following case
is more stringent
במין אחד ממינין הרבה bemin echad miminin harbe than many categories. What's
the case? שאם אכל חצי זית, she'im achal chatzi zayis, you ate
a half of a כזית kezayis of
חלב, chelev. וחזר ואכל חצי זית vechazar ve'achal chatzi zayis ממין אחד
mimin echad and you ate another half a כזית. kezayis. Now this
would all have to be within כדי אכילת פרס, kedei achilas pras,
which is I don't know five minutes or nine minutes, the time
it takes to eat half a loaf of bread, that's considered to
be one act of eating. So it's one state of forgetfulness which
could last weeks or months or years but it's also within a
few minutes so it's one act of eating. A half and a
half, if it's both of the same sin, both of the same
חלב, chelev, then they combine, חייב. chayav. משני מינין, mishnei minin, if
you ate half a כזית kezayis of חלב chelev, and half a
כזית kezayis of נותר, notar, then פטור, patur, then you're exempt. Like
okay, that's pretty obvious, they don't combine to be one sin offering.
תוספות Tosafos actually says it's not so obvious because there's a גמרא
Gemara that tries to somewhere that says that there could be like
this generic category of don't eat forbidden things so maybe different things
could combine. But we'll not but certainly not for קרבן korban purposes.
Okay, so that's the משנה. Mishnah. Okay? That if it's the same
types of things they combine for one
קרבן, korban, multiple acts combine for one, but two halves also combine
and different things never combine whether to be strict or to be
lenient. Now, והוינן בה. vehavinan bah. So so far no big deal.
והוינן בה, vehavinan bah, but we asked on this. ממין אחד חייב
צריכא למימר? mimin echad chayav tzericha lemeimar? When you ate half a
כזית kezayis of חלב chelev and half a כזית kezayis of חלב
chelev that that becomes one thing? That's a חידוש? chiddush? That two
חצי זיתים chatzi zeisim combine to one? I mean, okay, obvious. So
ואמר ריש לקיש, ve'amar Reish Lakish, so said Reish Lakish משום בר
טוטיני mishum Bar Tutini in the name of Bar Tutini, הכא במאי
עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון שאכלו בשני
תמחויין. kegon she'achalo beshnei tanchuyin. You ate each half of a כזית
kezayis of חלב chelev in a different food. One of them you
had in a stew and the other you had grilled. Okay? Now
it's exactly the same sin but maybe because at the sort of
experiential level they were very different types of foods, that's enough to
make it considered not two different sins but two different acts and
the two different acts don't combine. I don't combine eating my soup
with cutting into my steak even though both of them had חלב
chelev in it. Okay? So one minute, one minute. ורבי יהושע היא
דאמר תמחויין מחלקין. veRabbi Yehoshua hi de'amar tanchuyin mechalkin. And it's Rabbi
Yehoshua who says that different types of, you know, dishes separate the
act. So מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, אמר רבי יהושע בין לקולא בין
לחומרא, amar Rabbi Yehoshua bein lekula bein lechumra, I might have thought
that Rabbi Yehoshua says this idea that it separates the act whether
to be stringent or lenient. What does it mean to be stringent
or lenient? If you are well let's well I'll just finish then
we'll say it out. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so this
teaches me דלקולא לא אמר לחומרא קאמר, delekula lo amar lechumra ka'amar,
he only said it to be lenient, not to be... he only
said it... he did not say it to be lenient, only to
be strict. So how are you strict? If each one, if the
if the soup was a כזית kezayis of חלב chelev and the
steak was a כזית kezayis of חלב chelev and you're saying they're
separate acts then what am I obligated to do? Bring two קרבנות.
korbanot. If they were one act, one. So by saying they're separate
acts that's being strict. How would it be lenient to say they're
separate acts? Well, if the soup was a half כזית kezayis and
the steak was a half כזית, kezayis, by saying they're separate I'd
be off the hook. So the גמרא Gemara is saying I might
have thought that he applies his rule in both cases, separate them
both cases. No, he only applies this to be stringent not to
be lenient. So therefore in the case of two halves we would
combine them and say you do bring it. So what's the point
of saying this? So that so first understand when the משנה Mishnah
said if you ate two half כזיתים kezaysim of חלב chelev you
bring a קרבן korban and the question is isn't that obvious? No
it's not obvious because it could be a half a כזית kezayis
soup, a half a כזית kezayis steak. I might have thought that
the same way that could lead to two קרבנות, korbanot, it would
also get you off the hook here. No, that to be strict
we do combine it and consider it one act. Okay, so that's
how we read the משנה, Mishnah, the two half כזיתים kezaysim you
bring a קרבן. korban. For a קרבן. korban. But now we have
our question. You see that we do not apply the same rule
of because you divide for קרבנות, korbanot, you also divide the two
halves to get off the hook. Here you would divide it for
קרבנות, korbanot, but for the case of the two halves you would
combine it. So how can we here assuming if you divide it
here, you'll divide it in the case of two halves? So the
גמרא Gemara says, והכא vehacha here,
דחלוקים מחטאות, dechaluqim mechataot, the soup and the steak, if they're different
for different sin offerings, when they're a one and a one. דקמצטרפי,
dekamtztarfei, what we're saying is that if it's a half and a
half, you would combine it. So we don't have the same rule
for combining for קרבנות korbanot as opposed and compared to combining for
two halves. So אמר ליה מר, amar lei Mar, so he said
back, no, that's not a question to me. מר ארישא מסתני ליה
וקשיא ליה. Mar areisha masteni lei vekashia lei. You had this question,
aren't the two halves obvious, and you brought in this whole idea
of two different plates and dishes, and then you came up with
your conclusion that there's a difference between two halves and two wholes.
So and therefore you had your question. אנן
אסיפא מסתנינן לה. anan asseifa masteninan lah. We teach this at the
end of the משנה. Mishna. ולא קשיא לן. velo kashia lan. And
therefore we don't, we're not bothered, meaning how do we have the
discussion? Here's how we have the discussion go, right? Your question was
when you say two halves of חלב, chelev isn't that obvious? And
your answer is it's not so obvious because it's two different dishes,
etc., etc. That's not how we learn the discussion. Here's how we
learn the discussion. משני מינים פטור. mishnei minim patur. It's not the
case of two halves of חלב, chelev, a half of a כזית
kezayit of חלב chelev, and a half of דם, dam, blood, and
that you're exempt.
צריכא למימר? tzricha leimeimar? You have to tell me that? That's obvious.
You didn't do a whole sin. Half חלב chelev and half blood.
So ואמר ריש לקיש משום בר טוטיני, ve'amar Reish Lakish mishum Bar
Tutini, and here's where we bring in the issue of the dishes.
לעולם ממין אחד. le'olam mimiun echad. When we say two different things
don't combine, we don't mean a half חלב chelev and a half
blood. What we mean is half a כזית kezayit of חלב chelev
in the soup and half a כזית kezayit of חלב chelev in
the steak. That two different things don't combine, it's even the same
sin, חלב, chelev but if they're in two different dishes they don't
combine. ואמאי קרי ליה שני מינים? ve'amai kari lei shnei minim? Why
is it being called two different categories? שאכלו בשני תמחויים, she'achalo bishnei
tamchuim, because you ate them in two different dishes, one is a
soup and one is a steak.
ודם איננו דם, דם הוא באמת חלב? vedam einenu dam, dam hu
be'emet chelev? It didn't say דם.
dam. It says if you ate two halves of different categories they
don't combine. So we're saying categories here doesn't mean חלב chelev, and
דם, dam, categories means soup and steak and they don't combine. So
רבי יהושע היא, Rabbi Yehoshua hi, and it's רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua,
דאמר תמחויים מחלקים, de'amar tamchuim mechalkim, that he says that soup and
steak divide and would bring two separate קרבנות. korbanot. דקא משמע לן,
deka mashma lan, and it's teaching us דאמר רבי יהושע בין לקולא
בין לחומרא, de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua bein lekula bein lechumra,
that רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua's principle that soup and steak don't combine
is whether to be strict, like two קרבנות korbanot if you did
a whole unit in each, and whether to be lenient, you did
a half unit in each and therefore they do not combine and
you do not bring it. So everybody agreed that we taught this
idea of two different dishes, the soup and steak, on this משנה.
Mishna. But the question is for what purposes did we teach it?
Did we teach it to say that in the case of two
halves, they actually
do
combine? That רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua's principle that these are separate acts
is only to be strict, but when it's two halves, we're strict
as well and we say they do combine? Or is it the
opposite, to tell us that the two halves don't combine, and the
same way he separates these acts to be strict, he separates these
acts to be lenient? So this second approach that we are consistent
with defining them as separate acts, whether to strict or lenient, was
like we said before when we asked this question of the two
states of forgetfulness. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says מדסיפא מין אחד
ושני תמחויים, mide'seifa min echad ushnei tamchuim, since you said that last
case of not combining are really two halves of חלב chelev but
they're just two different dishes, steak and soup,
מכלל דרישא מין אחד ותמחוי אחד. michlal dereisha min echad vetamchui echad.
So we're going to get back to our earlier question. So when
it says the two halves do combine, it means not only they're
both חלב, chelev but they're actually the same dish, two halves of
a כזית kezayit of steak that has חלב chelev, in it. So
the גמרא Gemara says if that's true, מין אחד ותמחוי אחד צריכא
למימר? min echad vetamchui echad tzricha leimeimar? We're back to our old
question, right? Why do you have to tell me the fact that
the two halves do combine? You're saying when they don't combine it's
חלב chelev and חלב chelev but different dishes. So when they do
combine it's חלב chelev and חלב chelev in the same dish. Why
do you even have to say that? אמר רב הונא הכא במאי
עסקינן כגון שהיה לו ידיעה בינתיים, Amar Rav Huna, hacha bemai askinan
kegon shehayata lo yedia beintayim, ורבן גמליאל היא דאמר אין ידיעה לחצי
שיעור. veRabban Gamliel hi de'amar ein yedia lachatzi shiur. Ah, no. This
is to tell you a different case. There is a חידוש chiddush
that the two halves don't combine, even though they're both חלב chelev
and they're both in your steak. Okay, so here's your half and
here's your half. If it was steak and soup, right, steak and
soup, right, then we said that they don't combine and we'll be
lenient and consider those separate acts even to be lenient. Okay. But
we're going to say that it's soup and soup, so they, so
they should combine. The גמרא Gemara says so obvious, half and a
half, soup and soup, you ate it within the same amount of
time, same state of forgetfulness, of course they combine. What's the חידוש?
chiddush? So the חידוש chiddush is it's not the same state of
forgetfulness. Over here is where you had your lightbulb. Okay, I gotta
draw my little lightbulb. Here you realized, here you actually realized, here
you had your ידיעה. yedi'ah. Oh my god, I just had half
a כזית kezayis of חלב. chelev And then you forgot again and
ate the other half כזית. kezayis. Okay, somebody distracted you and you
kept on eating your soup. Okay, so anyway, you'd say we normally
say that being aware makes two categories. And it certainly makes two
categories for קרבנות. korbanot. If it was one and then you had
your lightbulb and then one, right, then that would be two separate
קרבנות, korbanot, that would totally divide. But here is a case where
even though it would be divided for two wholes, it's not divided
for two halves. Why? Because when you were aware of what you
did, you were not really aware that you had done a full
sin. You were aware that you ate a half of the כזית.
kezayis. That is not being aware that you did the sin. Half,
okay, you can't eat a half שיעור shiur also biblically, but it
is not the full sin of eating חלב. cheilev. So the reason
it doesn't divide here is not, is it inconsistent? Here it divides
because it's a different type of knowledge. A ידיעה yedi'ah of a
sin divides. A ידיעה yedi'ah of a half sin does not divide,
and therefore they would combine. So when we say the half and
the half combine, we say isn't it obvious? It's not obvious because
you became aware in the middle. But the reason this doesn't divide
is because it's not a ידיעה yedi'ah of a full sin, it's
only a ידיעה yedi'ah of half a sin. And that's what it
means by the line where it says הכא כגון דהוה ליה ידיעה
בינתיים ורבן גמליאל היא דרבן גמליאל דאמר אין ידיעה לחצי שיעור. hacha
kegon dehava lei yedi'ah beintayim veRabban Gamliel hi d'Rabban Gamliel d'amar ein
yedi'ah lachatzi shiur. Being aware that you did a half of an
amount, a half sin, is not saying being aware that you sinned
and therefore it does not combine, yes.
So when a משנה mishnah says שאם אכל חצי זית וחזר ואכל
חצי זית ממין אחד חייב? she'im achal chatzi zayis vechazar ve'achal chatzi
zayis mimin echad chayav? Yeah. There was no ידיעה yedi'ah in the
middle?
No, there is a ידיעה yedi'ah and even so you're חייב chayav
because this type of a ידיעה yedi'ah does not divide. That's the
חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is that even if you became aware
that you would bring it because that's a type of ידיעה yedi'ah
that does not divide. Okay, moving on. איתמר, itmar, it was said:
אכל שני זיתי חלב בהעלם אחד. achal shenei zeisei cheilev be'he'elem echad.
Okay, we're back to these scenarios of how many קרבנות korbanot you
do bring. Like I said, just hang in there. By שבת Shabbos
we'll be on the ל"ט מלאכות. lamed-tet melachos. Okay, אכל שני זיתי
חלב בהעלם אחד ונודע לו על הראשון וחזר ונודע לו על השני.
achal shenei zeisei cheilev be'he'elem echad venoda lo al harishon vechazar venoda
lo al hasheini. Now this sounds like what we've already discussed. Okay,
and basically there's a nice, there's a רש"י Rashi that goes out
of his way to say that the assumptions of this סוגיא sugya
contradict the assumptions of the previous סוגיא. sugya. Okay, you ate one
כזית kezayis of חלב cheilev. then one כזית kezayis of חלב, cheilev
right, בהעלם אחד, be'he'elem echad, one stage of forgetfulness, right, one stage
of העלם he'elem of forgetfulness, and then what happened? So you forgot.
Okay, and then you became aware, okay, so what happened? So here
we'll call this A and B, they're two single כזיתים. zeiseim. Okay,
so חלב בהעלם
אחד ונודע לו על הראשון וחזר ונודע לו על השני. cheilev be'he'elem
echad venoda lo al harishon vechazar venoda lo al hasheini. And then
you became aware first of A and then of B. Now, based
on what we said by the שבת Shabbos case of the grinding
and the what not, what was the assumption that we had said
then? When you became aware, right, one state of forgetfulness, you became
aware of A, this is redundant because you already became obligated in
a קרבן korban of חלב. cheilev, We would say one קרבן. korban.
Now we're going to see that that assumption of the previous סוגיא
sugya is being debated. Let's take a look. So רבי יוחנן אמר
חייב שתים, Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav shtayim, two קרבנות. korbanot. I don't
care that it's overlapping and redundant and the original sin was all
one state of forgetfulness, if the remembering is at different stages, that
divides the קרבנות. korbanot. So Michael's question, what if you remembered all
at once? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says yeah, when we say one
state of forgetfulness is one קרבן, korban, that's when you also remembered
at once. But if you remembered in two stages, two קרבנות. korbanot.
וריש לקיש אמר אינו חייב אלא אחת. veReish Lakish amar eino chayav
ela achas. Now you're חייב chayav in A and then that obviously
incorporates B, certainly in this case where it was all in the
same state of forgetfulness. So the assumption of our previous סוגיא sugya
was like ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, only one. This is debating it.
According to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, even in one state of forgetfulness,
if becoming aware happened at different stages, even if it's the exact
same type of sin, two separate קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara is going to look at this. Okay, so רבי יוחנן אמר
חייב שתים וריש לקיש אמר אינו חייב אלא אחת. Rabbi Yochanan amar
chayav shtayim veReish Lakish amar eino chayav ela achas. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says חייב chayav על חטאתו והביא al chataso veheivi because the
תורה Torah says for your sin you shall bring. For each separate
sin you have to bring a separate קרבן. korban. Now he doesn't
always say that if you remembered both at the same time it
would be one, but basically since your obligation of קרבן korban occurs
when you remember, so therefore every separate remembering is a separate for
a separate act is a separate קרבן. korban. So for each sin
you bring. וריש לקיש אמר פטור. veReish Lakish amar pattur. Resh Lakish
says you're exempt.
מחטאתו ונסלח לו. me-chatato v'nislach lo. From your sin you'll be forgiven
even if you only brought for part of your sin are you
forgiven. So when you bring קרבן korban A, right, that's only for
part of what you did. You did A and B. It's מחטאתו,
me-chatato, it's part of it. But nevertheless, that forgives you for the
whole category. Okay, in this special case where it was all done
in one state of forgetfulness and it was the repetition of the
same sin. Okay, so that's what he learns it from. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, הכתיב על חטאתו והביא, haktiv
al chatato v'hevi, what does he do with the פסוק pasuk that
sounds like it's a separate קרבן korban for each separate act? ההוא
לאחר כפרה. hahu l'achar kapparah. No, what that's about is not I
became aware of A and then B. I became aware of A
and then what did I do? Then I actually brought my קרבן.
korban. We'll have a nice little מזבח mizbeach with a fire and
my little קרבן korban is on it. Okay, that's your כפרה. kapparah.
What I actually did was I brought קרבן korban A. And then
I became aware of B. All right, you know, if this קרבן
korban was if this became if this obligation came after A was
completely done, then you have to bring a separate קרבן. korban. Okay,
but if you became aware of A and then B, if it
hasn't been brought yet, then A can represent both A and B.
Okay, if you became aware of A and B and then you
brought your קרבן, korban, so when you became aware of B the
inner obligation occurred, we say that obligation gets incorporated into A and
just bring one קרבן. korban. But when you brought when the קרבן
korban came in the middle you weren't yet obligated in קרבן korban
B. So this can't include B if you weren't yet obligated in
B. That's where it has to be separate קרבנות. korbanot. But if
it's before the כפרה, kapparah, then it all gets wrapped into one.
Okay, that's where he says it would be separate if it happened
if you remembered after the atonement. ולרבי יוחנן נמי הכתיב מחטאתו ונסלח
לו? u'l'Rabbi Yochanan nami haktiv me-chatato v'nislach lo? One minute, for for
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it also says from your sin, which suggests
that even a קרבן korban for part of the sin can count
for another part. How does he say that if he says A
and B always have to have separate קרבנות? korbanot?
So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha be-mai askinan, what
are we talking about? כגון שאכל כזית ומחצה
ונודע לו על כזית וחזר ואכל כחצי זית אחר בהעלמו שני.
kigon she-achal k'zayit u-mechtzah v'noda lo al k'zayit v'chazar v'achal k'chatzi
zayit acher b'helamo sheini. All right, so what's the scenario? The scenario
is not one and one. The scenario is you had one and
a half and then you had a half. Okay, so all right,
one state of forgetfulness or whatever, but then what happened is that
in the middle here, you remember you had an awareness, here's my
little lightbulb again, you had your awareness that you did the... it's
actually not it's not I'll have to draw it differently.
See what happened. Okay, you ate the one and a half. You
ate that. I'm sorry. You ate the one and a half. Okay,
then you became forgot, you forgot.
Then you became aware that you had done one. Okay, you had
done one from A. Then you had another forgetting and
I can only use the whiteboard so much, you know this is
an... then you had another forgetting as a separate act afterwards and
you did another half. Okay, so in this case, when I became
aware that I had eaten one, that was enough of an awareness
to bring a to bring a קרבן. korban. So here's my קרבן
korban for for my חלב. cheilev. Now, at this stage when I
did the half, I forgot that I had eaten this half. I
only remember I had eaten one כזית. k'zayit. I didn't remember I
also ate this other half of a כזית. k'zayit. Okay, so if
I'd forgotten I'd eaten this half you might say, okay, this half
and this half should combine, because this awareness was not about this
half, this awareness was only about the whole. So let these two
combine. The answer is they don't combine. Why don't they combine? Because
since I'm bringing a קרבן korban for the one and this is
only a half, that gets sort of like waived. That's included in
the one even though you didn't remember it, forget about the half
and therefore it does not combine. So that's a scenario where I
only brought for part of my sin. This קרבן korban is only
for the one, it's not for the half and I actually had
a half and a half, but I'm off the hook. Okay, because
this half gets thrown out and it doesn't combine with the other
half. So, I know, you gotta hold קאפ. kop. Anyway, כגון שאכל
כזית ומחצה ונודע על כזית, kigon she-achal k'zayit u-mechtzah v'noda al k'zayit,
you became aware of the one part of it and you forgot
about the other half, וחזר ואכל כחצי זית אחר בהעלמו שני. v'chazar
v'achal k'chatzi zayit acher b'helamo sheini. And then you ate another half
and you had still forgotten about the first
half. מהו דתימא mah d'teima I might think ליצטרפו litz-tar-fu let them
combine, קא משמע לן kamas-ma-lan that they don't. So that's a scenario
where you only brought for part of your sin and you get
off the hook. All right. Now we're gonna have one last go
at this. Let's take a look. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי,
Amar leih Ravina l'Rav
Ashi, said רבינא Ravina to רב אשי: Rav Ashi: דאידיע ליה קודם
הפרשה פליגי? d'is-yadei lei kodem hafrasha pligi? When we said backtrack, let's
forget this half business, it's very confusing. But when we said our
case of A,
B, right, they all forgot, right, forgetting, and then you became aware
and you had A and B. And according to רב יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, each one is a separate קרבן. Korban. Okay. Now, when we
let's take a look at what's the scenario that רב יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says they're separate קרבנות. Korbanot. So he says: דאידיע ליה קודם
הפרשה פליגי? d'is-yadei lei kodem hafrasha pligi? Do they debate before you've
even set aside the קרבן? Korban? ובהא פליגי, uv'ha pligi, this is
what they debate. דמר סבר, demar savar, one is of the opinion:
ידיעות מחלקות, yediot mechalkot, just being having being aware at separate times
makes separate קרבנות. Korbanot. ומר סבר: umar savar: הפרשות מחלקות, hafrashot mechalkot,
no, that doesn't divide. What would divide is if you actually set
aside and sanctified the קרבן. Korban. אבל לאחר הפרשה, aval l'achar hafrasha,
but if you actually had set aside the קרבן, Korban, מודי ליה
ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן דחייב שתים. modi leih Reish Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan
d'chayav shtayim. Maybe ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would agree. Meaning, what here
makes these separate? So first of all, you remembered at different times.
Here you remember and then you remember. Does that enough according to
רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to make them separate? Okay, and that's what
they debate. רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says remembering at different times separates,
and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says it doesn't. Let's say, though, not
only did you remember, but you actually set aside the קרבן, Korban,
right, let me draw a picture, but okay. Anyway, if you actually
had a הפרשה, hafrasha, right, you set it aside in the middle,
maybe then even ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would agree. Ah, designated קרבן
Korban A can no longer be rolled in, right? Once you've already
said this is for that sin, then you can't incorporate B. So
maybe the only debate when all you had that separated them was
different awareness. But if you actually set one aside, then maybe even
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would agree that then you can't incorporate B
into A. Okay, that's one way of looking at it. או דילמא,
o dilma, or
perhaps, דאידיע ליה לאחר הפרשה פליגי, d'is-yadei lei l'achar hafrasha pligi, that
actually, no, the debate is that you did set it aside, and
even there they debate. ובהא פליגי, uv'ha pligi, this is the debate.
דמר סבר: demar savar: הפרשות מחלקות, hafrashot mechalkot, רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says because you set it aside, that divides it into separate acts,
into separate קרבנות. Korbanot. ומר סבר, umar savar, and you can't incorporate.
ומר סבר, umar savar, and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says: כפרות מחלקות.
kaparot mechalkot. No, until you've brought the קרבן, Korban, you can always
incorporate the second into the first. Okay, so just setting it aside
does not prevent you from combining
them. אבל קודם הפרשה, aval kodem hafrasha, but if we hadn't set
it aside yet, then maybe מודי ליה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש, modi
leih Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish, then maybe רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would
agree to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that if all you did was
remembered at different times, דאינו חייב אלא אחת, d'eino chayav ela achat,
then you're only חייב chayav once, you don't חייב chayav two. או
דילמא, o dilma, and the third possibility is: בין בזו ובין בזו
מחלוקת. bein b'zo uvein b'zo machlokes. They argue both cases. Okay, so
just simply, right, in this scenario, רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says two
separate קרבנות, Korbanot, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says one. What makes for
רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan two separate? Is it just that you remembered
at different times, or maybe the only thing that makes it two
separate is because you designated a קרבן Korban after the first? And
that makes the second one independent. Or maybe he says both things,
and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish argues on both things. So three possibilities
what their debate is. Their debate is when all you did was
remembered, their debate was when only in the case when you set
it aside, or the debate is in both scenarios. So let's take
a
look. אמר ליה: Amar leih: מסתברא בין בזו ובין בזו מחלוקת. mistabra
bein b'zo uvein b'zo machlokes. It makes sense to say they argue
in both cases. דאי סלקא דעתך: de'ei salka daitach: קודם הפרשה פליגי,
kodem hafrasha pligi, if you say that they only argue in the
case of before you set it aside, אבל לאחר הפרשה, aval l'achar
hafrasha, if you actually designated A, מודי ליה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן,
modi leih Reish Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan, then ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would
agree to רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that that B does not get,
is separate and does not get incorporated since you set aside A
already. דחייב שתים, d'chayav shtayim, that you bring two. If that's true,
that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish agrees when you said actually set it
aside, אדמוקי לה קרא לאחר כפרה, ad'moki lah kra l'achar kapara, לוקמה
לאחר הפרשה. lokmah l'achar hafrasha. Then why did we have a whole
hard time saying, remember we said one minute, according to, according to
רב יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, when is the according to ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, when is the case that the תורה Torah says that you
have to bring for each one separately? Right, remember we asked that
question? The פסוק Pasuk says על חטאתו, al chatato, each one separately.
But we said according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, you're just bringing
one for all of them. When do you bring for each one
separately? And we said, no, no, you'd bring for each one separately
if you actually brought the קרבן Korban in between. So the גמרא
Gemara is saying why did we have to say if you actually
brought the קרבן Korban in between? Why didn't we say ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish would agree that you bring each one separately if you
designated the קרבן Korban in between? So since the example we gave
was when you brought the קרבן, Korban, not when you designated the
קרבן, Korban, it shows that we're assuming that when you designate the
קרבן, Korban, it was not enough to divide the acts for ריש
לקיש. Reish Lakish. Have I completely lost everybody at this stage? Yes,
I see Charlie that even you are looking blank. Okay. Let me
just try this. Let me just give me your attention one more
time. I'll try one more time, okay? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
you divide, you remembered at different times they divide, ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish says it's all one. What for רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, what
is the case where they divide? Is it just remembering at different
times divides, or maybe part of what divides it is that you
actually designated the קרבן korban in the middle? Now you remember that
the גמרא Gemara said that even ריש לקיש Resh Lakish would agree
that if you brought the קרבן korban before before B, that divides.
But what if you didn't bring it? What if you just designated?
Would he agree in that case? And the גמרא's Gemara answer is
it sounds like he wouldn't agree in that case, because why did
we have to say that he agreed and would read the פסוק
pasuk of separate when you brought the קרבן korban in between? Why
didn't we just say he would agree if you designated the קרבן
korban in between? So it shows that designating would not be enough.
Now רש"י Rashi asks an interesting question. רש"י Rashi says, what do
you mean because we gave this answer it shows? ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish never said when we were talking about it we said oh
well he would agree if you brought the קרבן korban that's what
he would do with the פסוק. pasuk. He never said those words.
So how can we use that to prove what the debate is
about? So רש"י Rashi actually says yeah, the fact that in the
ישיבה Yeshiva this was the discourse and this was the way we
had framed the issue shows that we had an assumption about what
the debate was and therefore that should dictate our understanding of the
parameters of the debate. It's quite fascinating about sort of being aware
that you're giving the answer, it's sort of what's that process called
when you read your assumptions into a text and then you learn
it back out from the text? Okay. Yeah well anyway.
And this is רבינא Ravina and רב אשי.
Rav Ashi. I know. So anyway so that's what anyway but that's
what's going on here. Since we gave that answer that shows that
the only case where ריש לקיש Resh Lakish agrees is when you
brought the קרבן korban in between, not just when you not just
when you set it aside. Okay. And now we're going to go
on. ואי אחר הפרשה פליגי. ve-ee achar hafrasha pligi. Now the other
way is also true. If they only debate after you set it
aside, אבל קודם הפרשה aval kodem hafrasha if you just remembered without
setting it
aside, מודה ליה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש modeh lei Rabbi Yochanan le-Resh
Lakish דאינו חייב אלא אחת. de-eino chayav ela achas. Right? Even רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan if you say even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan only
said separate when you set it aside in between. But if you
just, separate acts of remembering but did nothing in between, he would
agree it's one. If that were true, then let's go back and
ask about the assumptions we made before. אדאוקמי ליה בקרא בכזית ומחצה.
ad-ukmei lei bikra bikizayis u-mechtza. Remember we had that really complicated case
of one and a half, remembering a half because we wanted to
get an example where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say you only
bring one קרבן korban for multiple things. Why did we have to
be so complicated? לוקמי קודם הפרשה. lukmei kodem hafrasha. Why don't we
just give it in a case where before you set it aside?
So what we're doing is we are saying from the answers we
gave before, we can see what our assumptions were. But okay, those
were our assumptions, not necessarily the truth. But okay, anyway, so because
since we said ריש לקיש Resh Lakish would agree if you brought
the קרבן korban in between, it shows that setting aside the קרבן
korban would not have been enough to divide it. And from the
fact that we said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would have one קרבן
korban in this crazy case of one and a half and a
half, and we didn't say one קרבן korban as long as you
didn't set it aside in between, it shows that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan would say that
even without setting it aside it would be separate קרבנות korbanot or
we wouldn't have had to give the crazy answer we gave. So
the גמרא Gemara says that doesn't prove that doesn't prove it, even
though we're also just trying to prove what our assumptions were. But
the גמרא Gemara says ודלמא ספוקי מספקא ליה. u-dilma sfukei misapka lei.
Maybe the reason we gave those answers is because we didn't know
what the debate was. ואי תמצא לומר קאמר ve-im timtza lomar ka-amar
and we're saying if you were to say ואי תמצא לומר קודם
הפרשה פליגי, ve-im timtza lomar kodem hafrasha pligi, if you say that
they debate even without setting it aside, just being aware at separate
times divides it and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says two. So פליגי
ביה רבי יוחנן היכי מוקי ליה לקרא. pligi beih Rabbi Yochanan heichi
moki lei likra. So how would he ever have an example of
bringing only one for multiple things if he says that it's always
separated into two? So בכזית ומחצה, bikizayis u-mechtza, the crazy case of
one and a half plus a half. ואי תמצא לומר אחר הפרשה
פליגי ve-im timtza lomar achar hafrasha pligi and if you say that
they debate even after setting it aside and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
even then says one, ריש לקיש היכי מוקי ליה לקרא Resh Lakish
heichi moki lei likra when would רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan have you
bringing two? לאחר כפרה le-achar kappara if you actually brought the sin
offering. Okay. So basically the גמרא Gemara says you can't even prove
what our assumptions were. We were giving answers without knowing what the
debate was. But we said even if רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
two in the most extreme case without setting something aside, just being
aware at separate times means two, then the case he would say
one would be this one and a half plus a half scenario.
Even if ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says one in the most extreme
case of even setting it aside, it still combines to one, he
would still agree to two in a case of having brought the
קרבן. korban. At the end of the day, we don't know whether
they're debating that you did set it aside or you didn't set
it aside, but we've given answers regardless. Okay. And with that, thankfully,
we will end. But I do want to just show you again
the רש"י. Rashi. Who talks about that we're trying to prove something
from our own assumptions. Okay, so if you take a look at
רש"י Rashi which he says עד דמוקים לה לאחר כפרה ad demukim
lah le-achar kapparah about six lines before the lines get wide in
רש"י. Rashi. He says, כי ברחינן לעילא ריש לקיש הכי וחטאתו
והביא
ואוקימנא
שיטתיה דתלמודא לאחר כפרה, ki barchinan le-eila Reish Lakish hachi ve-chataso ve-heivi
ve-ukimna shitatei de-Talmuda le-achar kapparah, since the
גמרא Gemara had said that this was the context of the debate,
so שמע מינה shma mina now goes like three lines before it
gets wide, דפשיטא לבני ישיבה שסידרו הגמרא דלאחר הפרשה נמי פטר ריש
לקיש, depishita livnei yeshiva she-sidru ha-gemara de-le-achar hafrasha nami patar Reish Lakish,
that
you see that since the גמרא Gemara had framed the debate that
way, it's so very funny, it's like self-referential, you are the גמרא,
Gemara, but you know, there was time. So since we had been
framing the debate this way and this was like the official version
of how we were framing the debate, we see that our assumptions
of the debate were the following. But it's quite fascinating that we're
trying to figure out what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish said not from their words, but from our own assumptions
of how we have traditionally framed their debate. And in the end
the גמרא Gemara says even based on that you cannot exactly prove
what they were arguing. And with that we will end today. All
right. Like I said, one more day of this guys. Just hang
in there.